过去几年我开始看F1
So in the last couple years I really started to get into Formula 1.
虽说F1的速度、各国的风情和黑科技的赛车让我如痴如醉
And although the breakneck speeds, exotic locations, and high-tech cars drew me in,
但让我印象深刻的一点其实是它的整个转播
one thing always stood out to me, the way it's filmed.
在直升机俯冲镜头、身临其境的车内视角与赛道周围的其他几台摄像机之间
Between the swooping helicopter shots, immersive onboard angles,
and the scores of other cameras around the track,
让F1不仅是赛车运动的奇迹 更是一个工程技术的杰作
it makes F1 not only a racing spectacle, but a technical masterpiece.
在开始前 我先说句如果大家以前经常看我的频道
Okay before we get started, I just want to say if you've seen my channel before
然后奇怪我怎么开始做F1相关视频了
and are confused why I'm posting a Formula 1 video,
那是因为我的频道内容反映了我当前正沉迷什么
it's because I want this channel to reflect what I'm actually interested in.
而我现在的确沉迷F1无法自拔
And uh right now that happens to be Formula 1.
而如果有人因为F1进来看这个视频
And for anyone here just for F1,
而且反响还不错的话 那我肯定还可以多做几期
if the video does well and it gets a good good reception, I can definitely do more.
按你胃 本期视频我们将聊聊F1比赛中用到的各种摄像机
Anyways, in this video, we're first going to talk about the different types of cameras,
以及它们如何拍摄比赛画面
and how they're used to film the race.
还会了解麦克风、转播设备的物流统筹
Then we will touch on microphones and logistics.
最后还会了解F1转播的节目制作
And finally we'll break down the television production
及其背后将126个机位画面整合成现场直播画面的那群“军队”
and the army of people it takes to compile all 126 different camera angles into a seamless live broadcast.
另外 本期视频里的一些内容可能已经过时了
One quick thing to add is that some of the information in this video
might be slightly outdated or a little off,
但我已经尽我所能收集这些尽可能新的资料了
but I did the best I could finding reliable up-to-date sources.
而所有资料都会在视频详情里列出
But all of the sources I used will be listed in the description below.
直升机
好 先讲讲F1里可能用到的最贵的摄像机吧——直升机
Okay, first we're gonna break down probably the most expensive camera on the track, the helicopter.
无论是介绍整个比赛地点 还是跟踪赛场上的动态内容
Whether it's getting establishing shots of the race location or tracking the action from above,
这些画面都是非常有动感、有沉浸感的
you can be sure the footage is going to be dynamic and immersive.
因为直升机是一直运动的
Because the helicopter is constantly moving,
F1比赛使用先进摄像机稳定器来消除震动
Formula 1 uses an advanced camera stabilizer to smooth out any bumps.
摄像机会连接在控制平台
The camera is then connected to a control panel
直升机飞行员一边飞 摄影机操作员在另一边拍
which a camera operator can use while the pilot flies the helicopter.
俩人相互配合拍摄各种画面
The pair work as a team to get shots,
随时交流：该往哪飞、该拍什么
constantly communicating where the helicopter needs to be, and what the shot type is.
90年代F1首次引入直升机视角
Back in the early 90s when helicopters were first introduced to the sport,
那时还只是保持悬停拍一个静态视角
they would just simply hover in the air and get a static angle.
而现在直升机已经可以连续拍摄比赛的长复杂镜头了
Now the helicopter is constantly capturing long complex shots of the race
让观众随时能够了解到围场动态
that really give the audience context as to what's going on.
车载摄像机
车载摄像机可以提供那些最令人兴奋的比赛画面
Onboard cameras provide some of the most exciting footage of the race.
可以让观众身临其境
They allow the viewer to get right into the action
比那些固定摄像机更能让观众感受到赛车的速度
and are often better at depicting the insane speeds of the cars than the trackside cameras.
F1在1989年才开始正式引入车载摄像机
F1 only started routinely using onboard cameras in 1989.
在技术规范中规定 每辆车必须有五台车载摄像机
In the technical regulations it states that every car must have 5 on-board cameras.
两台在车顶T架上
2 of these cameras are located in the T-shape box on top of the car
一台朝前 一台朝后
with one facing forwards and the other facing backwards.
剩下三台分布在鼻翼和车身上
The remaining 3 cameras are placed on the nose and the chassis.
令人惊讶的是 这些摄像机的总重只有不到4磅(1.8公斤)
Amazingly, the total weight of these cameras is less than four pounds.
另外 F1目前正在试验在车上安装360度摄像机
One quick note to add is that F1 is currently experimenting with putting 360 cameras on the cars,
但目前这些画面只是在社交媒体上传播
but currently they're only using the footage for social media purposes
并没有在真实直播中使用
and not actually live race footage.
索道摄像机
围场里最后一个移动摄像机是索道摄像机
The final moving camera on the track is the cable cam.
位于维修区通道和终点直道之间
Located between the pit lane and the finishing straight,
索道摄像机架在一组索道上
the cable cam is a camera attached to a set of wires
可以以超过130km/h的速度移动 捕捉比赛画面
that can move at over 130 kilometers per hour to capture the race.
非常适合拍摄进出维修区的赛车
It's great for tracking cars as they enter or leave the pits,
或者拍摄大家发车时的动态画面
or providing a dynamic camera angle of the cars as they rock it down the straight.
索道系统俗称“飞猫”
The system they use is called the cam cat
和奥运会或者电影大片里用的是同款
and it's the same cable cam system used at the Olympics and in blockbuster movies.
赛道摄像机
赛道摄像机是F1赛事转播画面里的主要镜头来源
The trackside cameras are the bread and butter of the Formula 1 race coverage.
主要为了让观众了解赛事动态
They are essential for allowing the viewer to track the action
通常保持一个指向 让观众知道哪辆赛车在哪
and always staying oriented as to which car is where.
没了赛道摄像机 就很难实时了解比赛情况了
Without trackside cameras, it would almost be impossible to follow the race,
特别是当赛场上同时发生很多事件的时候
especially when there's multiple things happening at any given time.
整条赛道大约有25台赛道摄像机
There's usually about 25 of these cameras placed around the track,
具体数量会依赛道而定
but that number can vary based on the circuit.
F1使用Grass Valley的摄像机拍摄高清视频
F1 uses Grass Valley cameras which are able to capture high quality video
可以直接把画面传回播送中心
that can be sent directly to the broadcast center.
摄像机搭配的是佳能广播镜头
They pair these cameras with Canon broadcast lenses,
其中有些镜头焦距范围可以达到9-810mm
some of which are able to zoom from 9 mm, all the way in to 810 mm.
相当于90倍变焦
That is a 90 times zoom.
一个镜头要25万美元
These lenses can cost up to $250,000 each,
这辈子是买不起了
I will not be getting one anytime soon.
摄像机被放在云顿三脚架上 保证画面稳定顺滑
This camera setup is then mounted on a Vinten tripod head which is very robust and smooth,
可以捕捉飞驰而过的赛车
and is essential for capturing lightning quick whip pants as the cars zoom by.
呃……我想说的是……
Okay, quick side note …
刚才那大哥怎么拍的？
How is that guy getting that shot?
一个松果弹斗闪电鞭就把摄像机甩过去了
There's no way that looks good, he's just … just … just cranking it …
他要么是世界上最牛逼的摄像师
He's … He's got to either be the greatest camera operator in the world,
要么拍出来的就都是废片 我不好说了
or he's just getting garbage, I don't know.
许多车迷抱怨赛道摄像机不应该移动跟踪赛车
Many fans complained that the trackside cameras
should not pan to track the cars as much as they do.
因为相比于静态机位 跟踪机位会显得赛车很慢
As it makes them look slower when compared to a simple static shot.
但F1的顾虑是引入太多静态角度机位会让赛况的追踪更困难
However F1 is concerned that introducing more static angles would make the race harder to follow.
高速摄像机
在赛道摄像机中还加了几台高科技的高速摄像机
Mixed in with the trackside cameras are a few high-tech slow motion cameras
放置在赛道的几个关键位置
that are positioned at key parts on the circuit.
它们只用于回放录像
They are strictly used to replay footage
让观众在事故后能了解到发生了什么
and help the audience to see exactly what happened after the incident.
F1在之前比赛中使用的是Phantom v642高速摄像机
F1 has used the Phantom v642 high-speed broadcast camera at races before
可以拍摄每秒五……5850帧画面
which can shoot up to 5 … 5850 frames per second.
阿隆索2016年在澳大利亚翻车的慢动作画面真的太牛逼了
It's amazing to watch the footage back like in Alonzo's crash in Australia in 2016.
特殊摄像机
出了上述所说的各种摄像机
In addition to all the cameras mentioned so far,
还有很多其他的特殊摄像机分布在赛场上
there's also quite a few specialty cameras dotted around the circuit.
包括埋在赛道上的摄像机
These include several cameras embedded in the track
感受车轱辘高速碾到脸上的感觉
to show the speed of the cars racing over them.
五个不同的移动摄像机捕捉维修区内的戏剧性画面
Five different roaming cameras to capture any pit lane drama.
几个观众席位的摄像机捕捉大家的反应
A handful of cameras to record crowd reactions.
还有几个摄像机会捕捉进站换胎的镜头 比如视频中的俯视角度
And even more cameras capturing pit stops, like this top down angle.
还有一个是在剪叉式升降机顶端的摄像机
Another camera to quickly mention is one on top of a scissor lift.
通常在终点大直道的末端
Usually located at the end of the opening straight,
F1会派一名摄像师在顶上拍摄一票赛车冲向直道末端驶入一号弯的画面
F1 will send a camera operator high up on a scissor lift,
to capture a unique view of the cars heading down the straight, and down into the first turn.
最后算下来 一个比赛周末总共要用到126台摄像机
In total, there can be up to 126 different cameras filming the race during one weekend.
麦克风
所有精心设计的摄像机设置最终能捕捉到F1赛车的真正力量和速度
All the elaborate camera setups would fail to capture
the true power and speed of Formula 1 cars,
放置在赛道周围的147个麦克风还要占一半功劳
if it wasn't for the 147 different microphones placed around the track.
赛道的声音对车迷的观感至关重要
The sound of the race is critical for the enjoyment of the viewer.
实际上有一些研究已经证明
There have actually been several studies that prove
人们会把赛车的速度与其声音大小联系起来
people associate the speed of a car with how loud it is.
随着2014年混合动力时代的到来 许多车迷抱怨赛车声音太小了
With the start of the hybrid era in 2014, many fans complained that the cars were now too quiet,
没有之前的发动机标志性嘶鸣声了
and were missing their signature scream.
为了弥补那11分贝的音量损失
In order to combat the 11 dB drop in volume,
F1开始往车上装麦克风 以提高观感
F1 has recently began placing microphones on cars in order to boost the sound for viewers at home.
2018年 他们还首次推出了一种新型的麦克风
In 2018, they debuted a new type of microphone
安装于赛车下方 紧挨排气管
that sits underneath the car right next to the exhaust.
这个尺寸不到一平方英寸的微型麦克风
This tiny microphone measuring less than a square inch
可以承受高达120°C的温度
can withstand up to 120°C,
并能准确地捕捉到F1赛车的真实动力输出情况
and can accurately capture the true power of a Formula 1 car.
节目制作
虽说有了那么多机位和麦克风
While you can have as many cameras and microphones as your heart desires,
但要看到好看的比赛节目 还需要人来把这些音视频内容结合起来
you still need someone to combine all of the audio and visuals together to make a compelling TV program.
对于F1来说 那个人就是节目制作组组长
For F1 that person is the television production team leader.
他们就像指挥家一样 实时指挥编辑比赛内容
They're essentially a conductor editing the race together in real time.
他们的团队接管所有126个机位与147个麦克风
Their team takes all 126 cameras and 147 microphones,
将它们无缝组合成一套比赛节目
and combines them together to make a seamless production,
并实时直播出去
all while being LIVE on air.
让一个人关注所有事情是不可能的
It's way too much for one person to keep track of.
所以有不同的分小组来完成各自的画面内容
Instead, different teams make their own sub mixes
最后由节目制作组组长将画面统合起来
which the television production team leader then weaves together.
回放组挑选一些精彩瞬间的内容
The replays team handpick shots of exciting moments
在适当的时候进行回放
that can be replayed when there's an appropriate time.
赛道组完全使用赛道摄像机严格跟踪比赛进程
The track mix team strictly follows the race using just the trackside cameras with no added extras.
即使画面没给到他们也要整场跟踪下来
It runs the entire race even when it isn't being shown.
最后 一个小组负责主直播流 就是我们电视上看到的最终画面
And finally, there's a team in charge of the main feed, which is what the world sees at home.
他们会把赛道组、回放组和其它机位的摄像机统合起来
It combines the track mix and replays with all the other camera options,
比如直升机摄像机、车载摄像机、维修区机位等等
like the heli-cam, onboard cameras, or pit lane angles.
在看到团队合作将不同角度的画面组合起来后
After seeing footage of the teams working together to combine the different angles and mixes,
就能知道真正播出画面背后是怎样的奇迹了
it's an absolute miracle how seamless the race plays on TV.
[这段是各种导播喊话]
每个小组的导播都在跟摄像各种喊话切镜头
Each team director is either shouting camera angles to cut to,
找用于回放的片段
finding clips to use in replays,
或者试图在不同片段中拼出一个围场热点故事
or trying to find a cohesive story within the tangle of different narratives.
负责主直播流的人总是要问自己：我要怎么搞事
The person in charge of the main feed always has to ask themselves what story they're trying to tell.
如果是汉密尔顿对战维特尔
If it's Hamilton versus Vettel,
那维特尔撞车后就应该多拍拍他失落的画面
it's more important to stay on Vettel being upset after he crashes,
而不是去拍其他车驶入维修区
than to show several drivers going into the pits
F1更倾向于展现围场内的人情世故
F1 is always trying to show the emotion behind the race,
而不是把所有细节流水账般罗列出来
not necessarily every little detail of what's happening.
物流统筹
另一个我想说的是向50多个国家直播比赛背后所需的超牛逼的物流统筹
Another thing I wanted to talk about are the insane logistics needed to broadcast the race live
out to more than 50 countries.
因为很多赛道并没有专门的广播中心
Because most tracks don't have a dedicated broadcast center,
所以F1每场比赛都会把自己所有转播设备搬来
F1 transports all of the equipment needed to each race.
这些设备能装满两架747 或者26辆平板卡车
This takes up two jumbojets or 26 flatbed trucks.
比如2018年 当塞巴斯蒂安·维特尔赢得新加坡大奖赛后
For example in 2018, when Sebastian Vettel won the Singapore Grand Prix,
仅仅五天内 广播中心就被拆解 并在俄罗斯索契重新搭建完成
the entire broadcast center was torn down and rebuilt in Sochi Russia, in just 5 days.
结尾部分不翻了 感谢观看
Alright, that is the video, I hope you guys enjoyed,
and maybe  learned something you didn't know about the filming of Formula 1.
That video took an enormous amount of research.
I kind of got in over my head,
because nobody has actually ever compiled,
and to my knowledge, nobody has actually compiled how they film F1
into one article or video or whatever.
So hopefully this is the first.
If you're new here, consider subscribing, it really helps me out.
Or if you've been watching for a while and you haven't yet, please do, I would, I would love you forever.
Also if you enjoyed the video, you could leave a like.
And potentially a comment below.
What you thought of this video,
was anything inaccurate that I said that should be corrected,
or do you have anything else you could add to it that I might have missed,
as always you can follow me on instagram @tommydewit_
and I will see you guys in two weeks.
I do want to show you one thing … one sec …
Okay, I wanted to have this in the background.
But as you can see I have like a hundred different other photos so it didn't work.
But this is my dad's.
I don't know if you can see it.
It's of the Monaco Grand Prix,
and I thought I was going to be so sick, and I wore a racing t-shirt, also my dad's.
But yeah, I'm sad it didn't make it in.
Okay, I gotta wrap it up, I'll see you in two weeks.
I'm really struggling here, I've almost been recording for an hour and a half …